Guide to the William Force Stead Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1899-1963; Series II; 6.05; (19 boxes)
  - Prose Works
    - "Prose works: location of Stead given", undated; 2 (Box 24)
    - "Prose works: location of Stead given", undated (Box 25)
    - "Prose works misc.", undated (Box 25)
    - "Prose works misc.", undated (Box 26)
    - Portrait of Joe Jordan, undated (Box 27)
    - Elizabethan Religious Poetry, undated (Box 27)
    - The Revival of Lying, undated (Box 27)
  - Poetry
    - The Poetical Works of William Force Stead, 1900-1901 (Box 28)
    - "Poetry: miscellaneous", undated; 3 (Box 29)
    - "Poetry: fragments", undated (Box 29)
    - The Sunflower and Other Poems, undated (Box 30)
    - "Old Pullen and acknowledgements from "Wayfaring" with Blunden's criticism", undated (Box 30)
    - "Poetry with location of Stead (Eng.)", undated (Box 30)
    - "Poetry with location of Stead (US)", undated (Box 30)
    - "Poetry with dates", 1900-1928 (Box 30)
    - Approach to the Altar, 1934 (Box 31)
    - The Catholic Standard and Times with "Stages in My Conversion", 1930-1934 (Box 31)
    - Miscellaneous poems, undated (Box 31)
    - Windflowers and Other Works, 1911 (Box 31)
    - "Poems from the Bible", undated (Box 32)
  - Sermons
    - Sermons, undated (Box 33)
    - Sermons, 1917-1933; 3 (Box 33)
    - Sermon fragments, 1911-1921, undated; 3 (Box 34)
- Notebooks, 1876-1935, undated; Series III; 3.75; (9 boxes)
  Notebooks is arranged in three loosely defined subseries: Notes on Lectures and Other Topics; Notes on Religious Subjects; and Essays, Poems and Verses. Each subseries is further arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  The series consists of notebooks containing Stead's notes on a variety of subjects, including English literature; interpretations of the Bible; and the role of religion in modern England. Essays, Poems and Verses holds notebooks apparently containing drafts and draft copies of works by Stead, mainly untitled verses and verse fragments.
  - Notes on Lectures and Assorted Topics
    - "Body and Mind", undated (Box 35)
    - "Early English Poets", 1876 (Box 35)
    - "The English Lyric", 1920 April 26 (Box 35)
    - "Hamlet", undated (Box 35)
    - "Kant and other Lecture Notes", 1920-1921 (Box 35)
    - "Lecture Notes on English Authors", 1920; 2 (Box 35)
    - "Logos", undated (Box 35)
    - "Marcus Aurelius and Realism", undated (Box 36)
    - "Metaphysics", 1922 January 27 (Box 36)
    - "Places, Notes on", 1916-1928 (Box 36)
    - The Theory of Knowledge, 1922 May 2 (Box 36)
  - Notes on Religious Subjects
    - "Book of Romans, Notes on", 1915 (Box 36)
    - Croce, 1922 February 23 (Box 36)
    - "Epistle to the Ephesians, Introduction to", 1916 July 24 (Box 36)
    - "God the Creator...", undated (Box 37)
    - "The Holy Spirit in the New Testament...", 1919 (Box 37)
    - "Isaiah - Historical Notes", undated (Box 37)
    - "The Law and the Prophets...", 1919 (Box 37)
    - "Lecture Notes Religious in Nature", undated (Box 37)
    - "Mary Magdalen's Funeral Tears", 1936 March 13 (Box 37)
    - "Ontological Argument", 1922 January 27 (Box 38)
    - "Pax", 1935 December (Box 38)
    - "Publick Schools Religion", undated (Box 38)
    - "Recent Theistic Tendencies", 1919 April 29, undated; 2 (Box 38)
    - "Religious Essays", 1916, undated; 2 (Box 38)
    - "St. John's Epistle, Notes on", 1916-1917 (Box 38)
    - St. Nicholas, Vol. XXVII, No. 9, 1901 (Box 38)
    - "St. Paul's Epistles, Introduction to", 1919 May (Box 39)
    - "St. Peter's Ten Tears", 1935 July 9 (Box 39)
  - Essays, Poems, and Verses
    - "Draft of Christopher Smart ", undated (Box 39)
    - "Drafts of Letters and Essays", 1921 (Box 39)
    - "Essays", 1923 (Box 39)
    - "Essays", undated (Box 40)
    - "Higher Algebra and Verse", 1905 (Box 40)
    - "Invitation to Love (Verses)", 1946 (Box 40)
    - "The Legend of Tilly Flower Vale", undated (Box 40)
    - "Poems and Accounting", undated (Box 40)
    - "Poems and Essays", 1901-1905; 2 (Box 40)
    - "Poems and Essays", 1909-1932, undated; 3 (Box 41)
    - "Poems and Notes", 1916 June 23 (Box 41)
    - "Poetry", 1902 (Box 41)
    - "Poetry", 1923-1955, undated; 7 (Box 42)
    - "Verses", 1899 September 25, undated; 3 (Box 42)
  - Miscellaneous, 1907, undated
    - "College Notes", 1907 (Box 43)
    - "Miscellaneous", undated; 11 (Box 43)
- Personal Papers, 1891-1967, undated; Series IV; 3.55; (10 boxes)
  Alphabetically arranged by type of material. Two types, Foreign Language Material and Official Documents, are further listed in more detail.
  The series includes diaries dating from 1896 to 1928; papers relating to Stead's study of several languages; and records of his marriage and his work in the Consular Service. There are also address books, notecards and postcards.
  - Address Books, undated; 3 (Box 44)
  - Book Reviews, 1924 (Box 44)
  - Diaries, 1896-1902; 4 (Box 44)
  - Diaries, 1903-1913; 4 (Box 45)
  - Diaries, 1914-1918; 4 (Box 46)
  - Diaries, 1926-1928; 3 (Box 47)
  - Divine Moderations -Gradebook, undated (Box 47)
  - Foreign Language Material
    - French lesson book, 1909 (Box 48)
    - French vocabulary, undated (Box 48)
    - Greek lesson book, 1915 (Box 48)
    - Greek vocabulary, 1915 (Box 48)
    - Greek and Italian vocabulary with list of Parishioners, 1916 (Box 48)
    - Italian lesson book, 1912, undated; 2 (Box 48)
    - Italian vocabulary, undated (Box 48)
  - Ledger, undated (Box 48)
  - Music, undated (Box 48)
  - Notecards, undated (Box 48)
  - Notecards, undated (Box 49)
  - "Miscellaneous", undated (Box 49)
  - "Miscellaneous Notes and pressed flowers", 1911 (Box 49)
  - "Miscellaneous - All Contained in this Book was Written by WFS ", 1891-1892 (Box 50)
  - Official Documents
    - Certificates, 1916-1960 (Box 51)
    - Clippings, 1950, undated (Box 51)
    - Clippings and reviews, 1909-1938 (Box 51)
    - "Consular Service Papers", 1910-1919; 2 (Box 51)
    - Contracts, 1909-1937 (Box 51)
    - Contributions to periodicals, 1907-1967, undated (Box 51)
    - "Marriage clippings, etc.", 1910-1911 (Box 51)
    - "Scraps (Clippings)", 1933-1939 (Box 52)
  - Postcards, 1906-1959; 2 (Box 53)
  - University of Virginia Medal, 1906-1907 (Box 53)
- Photographs, 1910-1935, undated; Series V; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arranged according to original file titles.
  Photographs, including portraits of William Force Stead and family members.
  - "Aunt Mary", undated (Box 54)
  - "Early Oxford Pictures", undated (Box 54)
  - "Fitzhugh Coyle and Mary Farr Goldsborough, Home of", undated (Box 54)
  - "People", undated; 3 (Box 54)
  - "Places", undated; 2 (Box 54)
  - "Sean O'Sullivan Drawings", 1931-1935 (Box 54)
  - "Sean O'Sullivan Drawings", 1935, undated (Box 55)
  - "Stead, William Force", undated (Box 55)
  - "Yeats, John Butler", 1910-1920, undated (Box 55)
  - "Miscellaneous Photos", undated; 4 (Box 55)
- Keats-Shelley Memorial Association Papers, 1906-1950; Series VI; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Series VI documents Stead's long service as Honorary Secretary of the Keats-Shelley Memorial Association. The correspondence and document files concern the organization's support of the Keats-Shelley Memorial House in Rome and upkeep of the graves of the two poets at Testaccio. Box 57 contains a membership register.
  - Correspondence and document files, 1906-1939, undated (Box 56)
  - Printed material, 1911-1950, undated (Box 57)
  - Register of Members and Committee, undated (Box 57)
- November 1974 Acquisition (74.11.8), 1934-1958; Series VII; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arranged according to original file order.
  The acquisition includes personal papers, correspondence, including letters from Louis Golding, printed material, and religious memorabilia.
  - Background Information and Summary, undated (Box 58)
  - Drafts of Poems, 1958, undated (Box 58)
  - Joe Jordan, 1934 (Box 58)
  - Notes for Uriel and The Shadow of Mt. Carmel, undated (Box 58)
  - Correspondence
    - Beddoes, Vaughan Roscoe Minton, undated (Box 58)
    - Gaskell, Dorothy (Bagot), 1940-1960 (Box 58)
    - Golding, Louis (1895-1958), 1924-1934 (Box 58)
    - Hart-Davis, Sir Rupert Charles, 1907-, 1939 May 19 (Box 58)
    - Somerset, Henry Vere Fitzroy, 1950 (Box 58)
    - Tweedsmuir, Susan Charlotte (Grosvenor) Bachan, Baroness, 1882-, 1939 May 14 (Box 58)
    - White, Francis D., 1941 February 24 (Box 58)
    - Wilkinson, Cyril Hackett (1888-1960), 1950-1951 (Box 58)
    - Unidentified (Initials, Nick-Names, Etc), 1893-1969, undated (Box 58)
  - "The Art Club (Drawings, Etc)", 1897-1907 (Box 58)
  - "Framed Artwork of the Blessed Virgin", undated (Box 58)
  - The Queen's College Record, 1962 December (Box 58)
  - "Radio Oxford Tape about T. S. Eliot's Christening", undated (Box 58)
  - "Religious Memorabilia", undated (Box 58)
  - Rosary beads, undated (Box 58)
  - "Secretariat of State of His Holiness (Vatican City)", 1963 November 12 (Box 59)
  - The Trinity College Record, 1945, 1948 February; 2 (Box 59)
  - The Virginia Quarterly Review, 1928 April (Box 59)
  - Miscellaneous, 1848-1968, undated; 2 (Box 59)
- October 1975 Acquisition (75.10.6), 1978, undated; Series VIII; 0.21; (1 box)
  Typescript of a collection of poems by Stead.
  - The Sea Captain and Other Poems, undated (Box 60)
- May 1978 Acquisition (78.5.4), 1922-1948, undated; Series IX; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Chronologically arranged.
  The series consists almost entirely of letters from Stead to his father, Robert Stead.
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1922 January-June (Box 61)
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1922 June-December (Box 61)
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1923 (Box 61)
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1924 (Box 61)
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1925 (Box 61)
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1926 (Box 61)
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1928 January-June (Box 61)
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1928 July-December (Box 61)
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1930 (Box 62)
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1931 (Box 62)
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1932 (Box 62)
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1934 (Box 62)
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1935 (Box 62)
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1936 (Box 62)
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1938 (Box 62)
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1939 (Box 62)
  - Letters to Stead, Robert, 1943 (Box 62)
  - WFS to Marianne Stead, 1923-1935 (Box 62)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1922-1948, undated (Box 62)
  - "Miscellaneous - Literary", 1925-1948, undated (Box 62)
- December 1978 Acquisition (78.12.1), 1859-1960, undated; Series X; 1.46; (4 boxes)
  Material is arranged in no particular order.
  This series includes family correspondence; writings by William Force Stead; a film reel titled To Go to the Country; and five folders of notebooks by Stead's friend Henry Vere Fitzroy Somerset.
  - Letters from Stead, Edward to Stead, Robert, 1920-1922; 17 (Box 63)
  - Letters from Stead, Manning to Stead, Robert, 1922-1943 (Box 63)
  - A Short Biographical Dictionary of English Literature, 1929 (Box 64)
  - Faerie Queene, 1932 (Box 64)
  - The House on the Wold, 1930 (Box 64)
  - Moonflowers, 1909 (Box 64)
  - Verd Antique, 1920 July (Box 64)
  - Wayfaring Songs and Elegies, 1924 June (Box 64)
  - "Film Reel: To Go to the Country ", undated
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted, pending reformatting. The material may be seen only with permission of the appropriate curator.
  - "Seluzicki Collection", 1909-1970 (Box 65)
  - "AEG Rawlinson", undated (Box 65)
  - "Bookplates", 1903-1905, undated (Box 65)
  - The Great Republic Monthly, 1859 November (Box 65)
  - "Henry Vere Fitzroy Somerset Notebooks", 1898-1960; 5 (Box 65)
  - "Research Paper Written After 1928" (Box 65)
  - Miscellaneous, 1911-1953, undated (Box 65)
  - "Force-Stead Pedigree", undated (Box 65)
- Oversize, undated; 1.83; (2 boxes)
  - Photographs and drawings, undated (Box 66)
  - "Stead on Eliot", undated (Box 67)
- Restricted Fragile Material
  Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Film reel: "To Go to the Country", undated (Box 68)
- Printed Materials, Series XI; 7; (7 boxes)
  Material is unarranged.
  Series XI contains copies of printed works written by or once owned by William Force Stead. Boxes 69-74 contain volumes and items that have annotations, inscriptions, or accompanying notes. Box 75 contains unannotated volumes.
  - Annotated printed materials, 12 (Box 69)
  - Annotated printed materials, 8 (Box 70)
  - Annotated printed materials, 20 (Box 71)
  - Annotated printed materials, 8 (Box 72)
  - Annotated printed Materials, 12 (Box 73)
  - Annotated Printed materials, 9 (Box 74)
  - Printed materials (unannotated), 22 (Box 75)